Hi everybody welcome back to the channel,
today we're going to talk about how to use
a Sous Vide to prepare your ice cream base.
First things first, for those that don't know
what a Sous Vide is, it is a water circulator
that heats the water up at the same time and
keeps it there at that temperature for whatever
length of time you set it for. It's been used
in high-end restaurants for years and probably
for the last 10 years, they've become reasonably
popular in a home environment they're excellent
for cooking things like steak... steak is
excellent because if you know the internal
temperature of how you like your steak then
you can set the water to that temperature,
cook it for the relevant amount of time then you
know that your steak isn't overcooked and chewy,
remove it from there and then sear it in a pan as
you would do normally then you've got a perfectly
cooked steak you don't have to worry about
internal thermometers and you know if someone
talks to you and you've overcooked it by a couple
of minutes I've had my Sous Vide for probably just
over a year here, I have one back in the UK you
can get them with Bluetooth and you know... apps
and stuff like that. You don't need those but you
know... buy what's right for you. So in today's
video we're going to prepare an ice cream base
using our Sous Vide and during that time I get
to talk about the sponsor of the video.. Vevor now
Vevor have kindly supplied me with this commercial
grade vacuum sealer. So when you do Sous Vide, you
seal that up into a vacuum bag, we'll talk about
that in a minute you don't need one this big.
I for years used a tabletop one they're okay,
they do the job, they take a while and they don't
extract as much air as one like this so what we're
going to do is get this machine set up, It's
not even been used yet, talk quickly about the
process, make an ice cream, churn it as quickly
as we can now although this machine was given to
me I'm not going to automatically say it's great,
I will give you an honest opinion. There's a lot
of people that watch this channel that own ice
cream scoop shops, ice cream businesses and a lot
of people use these in the US to just increase
the longevity of their food. You can use these
to store anything, so if you make something
let's just say, this is an ice cream channel,
if you make ice cream cones it's a bit of a pain
to set it up clean it pack it away for you know an
event or whatever it might be using something
like this you can actually make them in bulk
and and then you can just vacuum seal them up
and put them in a Cupboard they'll last years,
you can do this for pretty much anything, so
anything that deteriorates with oxygen can be
made to last huge amounts of time. Beef jerky,
I eat a lot of beef jerky this is a great way
to store that make it get it down to the moisture
level that you need and then store it in a vacuum
sealed bag it will outlast any that you buy in the
stores by a Kentucky mile... I don't know where
that saying comes from, if you're from Kentucky
let me know! So we need to prep this we need to
clean it and I think I need to read the
instructions so let me have a quick read
and I'll come back to you.... reasonable it's
kind of what you'd expect from a Chinese company
the translation is okay. One thing I did note
is there's something here where it says the
opposite of actually what you want to do. It
says we need to fill the pump with oil first,
it came with the oil, it says remove the fixing
bolt from the back of the machine... fine.... then
it says "TURN ON" the machine and actually what
it should say is "TURN OFF" the machine because
what we're going to do is we're going to open
this thing up we're looking at this currently
the inner workings if you turned it on like
the instruction said you are putting yourself
in danger so please make sure that your machine
is not plugged in and not turned on all right we
don't want anyone to get get hurt so that's
problem number one the instruction manual so
what we need to do according to the instructions
is let me lower the camera a bit so you can see it
better is we need to fill this up so
the oil level is around half it says
specifically here not lower than 1/2, not
higher than 3/4 on this window so that is
what we can do we've got our lid off it came
with the oil there we go there we go that is
how much I had to put in there so we're down to
about 140 milliliters I'd say that's pretty much
spot on where it needs to be so we've got
some top up oil left that we can store away
for now so with our oil level exactly where
it needs to be we're going to clean the top
here like so making sure no debris
goes in we've got our little o-ring
that's on here as well make sure
that stays on and then let's fit
that not too tight but tight enough there we
go we're prepped so with our oil level filled
we can close our machine back up this is a
first for the channel big big sponsor Viva
so um when speaking to them about this machine
you know I spoke to a few of my customers for
polarized creamy and a couple of people
that support on YouTube and they own ice
cream scoop shops so it's not all about home
it's also about commercial I help people with
their businesses and a home ice cream making
it's a full service thing that I have going on
If you're not interested in this you can prepare
an ice cream base in exactly the same way but as
this is the first Sous Vide video, we're going
to talk through the whole process so there we
go that is our machine ready to be used so
if you've never used a sous vide machine
you need to vacuum pack the product that you
put into it so for us ice cream you can buy
in rolls like this um this one is actually
a tiny little bit too big for this machine
yeah it's it's about 1cm, 10 mm too big but lots
of different sizes of vacuum bags you can get
them pre-sealed at the end um this because I use
this for commercial environments when I go to my
customers locations I just make this to the size
required and then I run the machine and seal it
I'm going to show you how this process works
before we actually get onto the ice cream
so we've got 500ml, 500g worth of water
I've already sealed the end of this bag
we're going to assume that this is our ice
cream base we lay it in our machine like so
lift up the bar put the bar back down and
close the lid like so you can change the
time of the vacuum process you can change the
time of the ceiling time you can also change
the time of the cooling as well the cooling is
once the bag end has been sealed how much time
it remains there in place until the bar drops
down so all we have to do to start is press go
you always just rest your hand on the top and
you can see this gauge now and there it is,
our bar up our sealed bag of ice cream base with
no air in there at all it's done a really really
good job the small machines that are a couple
hundred dollars on Amazon they do a terrible
job of sealing this up you get pockets of air
throughout but this one has done a really nice job
it's taken all that air out a really nice sealing
job so considering this is obviously a liquid if
you do this with a solid it's more obvious to the
eye how much air has been taken out this has done
a really really nice job of this so we know
that that's 500ml we can get more in there so
that is how a vacuum sealer works this one is
really nice I'm really really happy with with
how this one operates with that in mind I wish
there was one function on this that it doesn't
have and that is just to seal the bag on its own
without running the vacuum without running the
entire process of vacuum sealing if you use the
rolls of vacuum bag like I do you want the means
to seal that bag on its own and uh some of the
other machines you can put the bag in like that
press seal and it will just seal it straight off
for you so you can you can do that with this you
can go into the settings adjust the time with the
vacuum to zero and then you can seal your bag but
it would be really nice to have just a heat sealed
button on the front there so we can press it will
seal the end of the bag and then we're good to
go but that's probably the biggest downsides
two downsides maybe three it's really heavy but
it's a commercial grade machine so it's probably
it's probably a little bit heavier than the
musso but hey I'm going to enjoy using this
one for now what we're going to do is get
this off the top we're going to prepare
an ice cream base right so the first thing
we need to do is fill up our container with
water so I filled that up to 4 quart or 4 L
basically the same thing there's a there's ever so
slight difference between a quart and a liter but
it's just not not enough to worry about so what
we now need to do is to get our sous vide in our
water and so we're going to set the temperature to
80C which is about 175F for 50 [Music] minutes
so our machine is circulating if you've never
tried tried uh SV before here you go I'll take a
video so you can actually see what's happening the
water is moving around those holes down the bottom
are they contain a heating element and they also
have the little propeller that moves that water
around mine is this brand it works absolutely
wonderfully I don't need to stress about it at
the top we can see the current temperature is
105f we're going for 175 so we're just going
to leave that to take over while we do that
let's prepare our base we're going to do a boozy
Maple gelato so I bought this Wayne Gretzky Maple
Canadian cream we would call this liqueur back
in England call it whatever you like liquor... I
don't care what you call it but this is the stuff
this stuff gives me serious acid when I drink it
on its own so we're going to use it in this.
I've balanced this recipe to reduce the amount
of sugar, can you substitute allulose
and xylitol in here.. allulose maybe,
you'll need to reduce the amount a little bit,
xylitol no because when we use xylitol, we have
to reduce the amount by almost 50% actually to
some degree it's a little bit more and because
the alcohol in this will affect the freezing point
or the PAC if you will, if you're getting into the
the science of ice cream, we can't add too much
of it which means our solids become really low so
the solids in this is down to I'll put the numbers
up on the screen in a minute but it we're kind of
like low 30s which is really as low as you want
to go when I tried to balance this with xylitol
we got solids down to about 24% which is just
too low so with that in mind all we need to do
while this is preparing is mix up our ingredients
I mean yeah you've got to have all this gear but
people want to see different ways of making ice
cream ,this is it. 660g of milk and that's 2% milk
you can use whole milk it's fine, and we're
going to use 120g of our 33% whipping cream,
and into that we're going to add our 40g of
skim milk powder, we're going to mix our sugar
with a stabilizer because of the solids being so
low, my recipe back up, because the solids are
so low we need to stabilize this recipe there's
a lot of free water in here so we're going for
126g of sugar, not a lot of sugar, into that we
are adding (if I can get the lid off) 4 .5g of
my stabilizer blend this is not my stabilizer
blend this is special ingredients stabilizer
blend if you are using if you using just Guar or
Xanthan reduce that down to about 3.5g otherwise
you might end up over over stabilizing it we don't
want that. So with our dry ingredients, I need to
get a new mini whisk.... in there we're just
going to stir our sugar and our stabilizer
together got a lump there
let's get that out there we
go and put that in there final ingredient
is our Maple Liqueur 100g here we go 100g
this is 17% alcohol it smells delicious.
Maple is a big Canadian thing but it's not
as it's not as crazy big as people want you to
believe but there's a lot of places to get it,
don't buy the cheap tourist Maple stuff that they
sell at the tourist locations buy something decent
so with that in mind we can stir this up one thing
I should have done and I forgot is try and put
your sous vide container on something a towel
a trivet, anything just a kind of it has been
known in the past for some of containers to crack
certain countertops quartz can do it marble won't
do it Granite shouldn't do it remember you're
heating things up to close to 100° Centigrade just
for some cooking things this is 80° Centigrade so
it shouldn't have any negative impact on anything
but better to be safe and sorry so we're mixing
this up here we're at 150F now so we're getting
close I can feel that the sugars now dissolved
skim milk powder's dissolved in goes our Maple
liqueur, so it's a strong flavor we don't want to
go any higher than and there's our base let's move
some stuff out the way because what we now need to
do is prepare a vacuum bag so I'm going to use my
Vevor vacuum sealer here if you have bags already
ready to go then find the one that [Applause]
fits we're going to seal this off definitely a
negative point of this machine is you need to
have the vacuum set to something it won't seal
this bag it won't put that arm up and seal this
bag if you set the vacuum to zero so even if you
set it to 5 seconds it's going to it's going to
help so there's our bag what we now need to do
is to get our base in here you can do this in
a couple of ways some people struggle doing this
but however you do it it's completely up to you I
like to just put the bag into something like this
and pour it in this is 1L so this is going to tell
us whether our vacuum sealer will take a 1L bag
we're going to change our setting to 35 seconds
on vacuum time again bags will float in sous
vide or sometimes they will float so if you can
get something heavy these are sous vide weights,
just pop one in there their food grade it will go
in there and will stop your bag floating in your
water so there is our mix we're going to put it
in here let's see if this will you lean down on
the top just for a couple of seconds until that
vacuum starts then you can let go well it will not
cope with one liter of Base this machine that's a
shame that is everywhere that's going to take some
serious cleaning up 5 hours later turns out that
that was just too much for that vacuum bag one
liter of liquid in that bag was not going to
happen so you will figure out the maximum amount
of size required for your bag new machine got to
figure it out somehow doesn't say in the
instructions we ended up losing about 200g
worth of mix because what happened was the smaller
bag, when filled up with one liter of our base,
just went everywhere in the machine before the
seal took place so you've got certain size bags
will take a certain amount of liquid you've got
the size of your machine that will determine
how much liquid or contents you can do liquid is
always difficult but we got to figure this out.
Anyway our remaining base, let's do this again so
my other vacuum sealer can deal with 1L of mix in
that size bag and it's much smaller, so we'll
do 20 seconds worth a seal let's see if it goes
again okay it seemed to deal with that much
better so that's 750g give or take 800g in
a bag that is that looks like a 10in bag to
me so with that in mind let's carry on we've
got our sous vide working here, temperature's
right, we've got our weight in our bag all we
can do is just pop that inside like that with
the weight in it's put our bag right down the
bottom we are just going to leave it in there
now for 40 to 50 minutes and I am going to tidy
up all this [__] mess so all we need to do
we got ice bath here we're going to take this
out pop that in there you can cool these mixes
down really really quickly because you can make
them thinner in the bag and that means that the
heat transfer happens much faster so with that
in mind we're going to I'm calling down really
nice and quickly we're going to age this in the
fridge going to age this for 24 hours let that
flavor of the maple come out of this alcohol
we haven't burnt off any of the alcohol doing
this because it's all encapsulated within the
bag when we cook alcohol on the hob you lose
a lot of that alcohol that Vapor comes off the
ethanol Vapor comes out it can do funny things
to the recipes. You start burning off some of
alcohol and if you're accounting for that in
your recipe for PAC so scoop ability it it can
play silly buggers with you so let's put this
in the fridge at least 24 hours I mean it's
Friday it's midday I'm going to go out my bike
probably won't get back to this until Monday,
so 3 days in a fridge, so have a good
weekend I'll see you in a couple of days.
So I lost the audio for this bit but essentially
all I'm saying is it's Tuesday I'm going to cut
the corner off of my sous vide bag, load it into
my ice cream machine and get it churning as normal
then when that's done get it dished up
into a container and popped it in the
freezer right it's been a couple of
days can smell that Maple coming out let's
get some dished up and into this bowl
fancy new spinny thing, look at that
glorious texture scooped perfectly no
dryness looking forward to trying this
one, fancy little spinny thing right
as I say smell of that Maple
coming through oh beautiful
texture oh that's so
good Ultra smooth super super smooth cuz it's
gelato we have higher levels of stabilizer
because there's a lot more water a lot less
fat in a normal American style ice cream
you would use you know 0.1 0.2% you'd
use 1g maybe 2g Max per kilo of Base,
Gelato though you can double that and maybe even
a little bit more it's got the perfect amount of
maple flavor this alcohol let me just grab it the
Wayne Gretzky Maple lure or Lor depending on where
you are in the world 17% alcohol use anything
that is approximately 17% alcohol content you
could probably get down to 14% Maybe go up to
20% I wouldn't go any further than that because
you're going to really mess up the freezing point
of this recipe so with that in mind there's loads
of liqueur/liquors that have this kind of alcohol
content, Bailey's being one of them so give this
one a try delicious Maple boozy gelato made in
a sous vide with our sponsor Vevor supplying
the chamber vacuum machine, worked amazingly a
couple of little things really that I wish it had.
I'm going to keep playing with the Vevor
vacuum chamber because I quite like using
the sous vide and I get asked all the time
to make recipes in different kind of ways so
sous vide is another wonderful way of doing it
we can do some really nice special things with
that as well so if you want to see some more of
these recipes then let me know in the comments,
thanks very much for watching don't forget to like
and subscribe... it's Fall or Autumn that means
the last fires and I've got something special
coming up for that so see you next time [Music]